<?xml version="1.0"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
 
  <title>www.mehulkar.com</title>
  <link href="http://www.mehulkar.com/"/>
  <link type="application/atom+xml" rel="self" href="http://www.mehulkar.com/atom.xml"/>
  <updated>2014-12-30T14:12:54-08:00</updated>
  <id>http://www.mehulkar.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name>Mehul Kar</name>
    <email>mehul.kar@gmail.com</email>
  </author>

  
  <entry>
    <id>http://www.mehulkar.com/goals/2014/03/12/2014-goals</id>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="http://www.mehulkar.com/goals/2014/03/12/2014-goals/"/>
    <title>Goals for 2014</title>
    <updated>2014-03-12T08:18:49-07:00</updated>
    <author>
      <name>Mehul Kar</name>
      <uri>http://www.mehulkar.com/</uri>
    </author>
    <content type="html">&lt;h3&gt;Hi&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some quantifiable goals for 2014 in no particular order&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;#### Language

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Go through all &lt;a href=&quot;https://livemocha.com&quot;&gt;LiveMocha&lt;/a&gt; Spanish Courses&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Learn C (&lt;em&gt;needs to be quantified&lt;/em&gt;)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;#### Guitar

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Master pentatonic scales across the bar&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Play 5 mins at an open mic night&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;#### Fitness

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;6 minute mile&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Gain 20 lbs&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <id>http://www.mehulkar.com/business/2014/03/01/auxiliary-business</id>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="http://www.mehulkar.com/business/2014/03/01/auxiliary-business/"/>
    <title>Auxiliary Business</title>
    <updated>2014-03-01T09:14:00-08:00</updated>
    <author>
      <name>Mehul Kar</name>
      <uri>http://www.mehulkar.com/</uri>
    </author>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;I was reading a recent &lt;a href=&quot;https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=7324236&quot;&gt;Ask HN&lt;/a&gt; and noticed that I was immediately
not interested in companies that did anything involving analytics or more
generally, any kind of data collection. My reaction on reading the homepage
of any of these companies was usually:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Oh great, another one of these.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I tried to explore my thoughts about this and realized that my disinterest
wasn&amp;#39;t specifically towards analytics or data collection&amp;mdash;I think history
is awesome and quantifying it into data points is even more awesome.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But from the standpoint of a company and its mission, this is
not exciting because data cannot exist in isolation; after all, someone
has to generate data for it to collected and analyzed. I call these analytics
and data collection companies &amp;quot;Auxiliary Businesses&amp;quot;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote class=&quot;twitter-tweet&quot; lang=&quot;en&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Seems like too many people, public and private sector, are making a living slicing the pie rather than baking it.&lt;/p&gt;&amp;mdash; Naval Ravikant (@naval) &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/naval/statuses/360890615896092673&quot;&gt;July 26, 2013&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;script async src=&quot;//platform.twitter.com/widgets.js&quot; charset=&quot;utf-8&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Auxiliary businesses exist as a layer on top of the
companies that are doing work. (I want to choose my words carefully here
because, I don&amp;#39;t think that these auxiliary businesses are doing work that is not
worthwhile. I also don&amp;#39;t think that they are not worth working &lt;em&gt;for&lt;/em&gt;.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But I think that once you build one layer of auxiliary business,
you can build any number of layers on top of &lt;em&gt;that&lt;/em&gt; layer; i.e.
analytics for the analytics company.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I believe this is a slippery (but probably profitable) slope and
can result in the stagnation of progress in areas that deserve more attention.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <id>http://www.mehulkar.com/life/2014/02/25/being-comfortable-with-being-unconfortable</id>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="http://www.mehulkar.com/life/2014/02/25/being-comfortable-with-being-unconfortable/"/>
    <title>Being Comfortable with Being Uncomfortable</title>
    <updated>2014-02-25T12:14:00-08:00</updated>
    <author>
      <name>Mehul Kar</name>
      <uri>http://www.mehulkar.com/</uri>
    </author>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;I&amp;#39;ve decided to start writing again.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have an oscilating level of self worth. There are times
when I believe that I have very important things to say,
and there are times when I would be loathe to voice an opinion,
much less put it in print.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In my Sophomore year of college (not too long ago) I started
a blog called &amp;quot;Thoughts, Uncited&amp;quot;. The idea was that I was a person
and I had thoughts and I would write them down and they would be
completely mine. I had just read &lt;em&gt;The Fountainhead&lt;/em&gt; by
Ayn Rand, and I was convinced that my opinions mattered by virtue
of them being mine. After two articles, I ran out of steam and
&amp;quot;pivoted&amp;quot; (before I really knew what it mean &amp;quot;to pivot&amp;quot;)
to brand &lt;em&gt;Thoughts, Uncited&lt;/em&gt; as a publication that would
collect such uncited thoughts. Despite getting a logo designed for $50,
that also, did not last.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My second attempt at writing was called &amp;quot;Off The Record&amp;quot;. This time,
writing was the means by which I organized my thoughts and made sense
of things I observed around me. I attemped to ask questions or follow
streams of logic and arrive at insights. It was a very useful exercise,
but at some point, I became both self conscious and bored.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My last attempt at writing in college was presumptous; I wanted to educate
others. I thought I had things figured out, and I wanted to tell other people
about it. I remember walking into our &lt;a href=&quot;http://royalpurplenews.com/&quot; title=&quot;Royal Purple News&quot;&gt;University newspaper&lt;/a&gt; and
telling the Editors that I wanted to be a writer. I had no journalistic
experience, but I had a blog and felt entitled. I even had the
gall to demand a column. Of course, the answer was a diplomatic
&amp;quot;Are you serious? No.&amp;quot;, but they let me publish two articles
before I quit.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was here that I first got a sense of what it was like to be unqualified.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When I joined the software industry, I stopped writing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I didn&amp;#39;t stop immediately. I wrote about how I launched my first Rails app.
I wrote about random weirdness I discovered in Javascript. I wrote about how
to configure a PostgreSQL server for a Rails app (because I would always forget).
But the more I learned, the more I realized that all the things I would write
had already been written. More importantly, they were things everyone I respcted
in the industry already knew. Sure, some people argued that there are
always people who were &amp;quot;a few steps behind&amp;quot; and it would be helpful for them if
I continued writing. But that argument never held, because I didn&amp;#39;t think I
was writing anything original.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I stopped writing because of an overwhelming attack of &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Impostor_syndrome&quot; title=&quot;Imposter Syndrome Wikipedia Article&quot;&gt;imposter syndrome&lt;/a&gt;.
Working in this industry has made me keenly aware of how much
I don&amp;#39;t know&amp;mdash;especially things that I&amp;#39;m really &lt;em&gt;supposed&lt;/em&gt; to know. To combat
this feeling of inadequacy, I taught programming as a volunteer and drank in
as much as I could through conversations with other software developers
(all of whom seemed years ahead of me). But ultimately, I stopped
writing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is not to say that I was feeling less confident--every time I tell
the story of coming out to California and joining a bootcamp to
change careers, I feel decidedly badass and I don&amp;#39;t mind giving myself
the credit for it&amp;mdash;but I was in the industry now. And I didn&amp;#39;t think I
had much to contribute. So I kept my thoughts--cited or otherwise--to myself.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Recently, I&amp;#39;ve discovered that the hesitation to stop writing is not a lack of
confidence or competence. Rather, it is a lack of comfort. In college, I wrote
either with a wild carelessness (&lt;em&gt;Thoughts, Uncited&lt;/em&gt;), or about things I knew well, i.e.
my own thoughts (&lt;em&gt;Off The Record&lt;/em&gt;). Both were comfortable because once I hit the
publish button, I could forget about it. I think that was a fundamentally different
(if not wrong) approach to writing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Taking a step back, I don&amp;#39;t think writing, or, more generally, creating is
about creating.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I think creating is about practicing being comfortable with being uncomfortable.
It&amp;#39;s about being vulnerable. A nice externality of experiencing real
vulnerability is personal growth. But I think there&amp;#39;s even more to it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I think that vulnerability is a universally appealing and binding emotion.
For example, I used to think that the Classic Underdog Story was appealing because
it was about the triumph of good over evil, but the more I think about it, the less
sure I am about a Universal Good, so it cannot explain this universal appeal.
I think the Classic Underdog Story is about identifying with some deficiency
in a protagonist, recognizing their attempt to challenge that deficiency (usually by becoming
vulnerable in some way) and then transposing the victory into our own life when
the deficiency is removed altogether. The part where the protagonist becomes
vulnerable is the part where we (or at least, I)
form the deepest emotional connection.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Underdog Effect is pretty well documented and studied by psychologists,
but framing it in the context of vulnerabilities has helped me understand
the &lt;a href=&quot;http://sethgodin.typepad.com/seths_blog/2010/01/quieting-the-lizard-brain.html&quot; title=&quot;Seth Godin on Quieting the Lizard Brain&quot;&gt;lizard brain&lt;/a&gt;, or &amp;quot;The Resistance&amp;quot;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The resistance is the voice in the back of our head telling us to back off,
be careful, go slow, compromise. The resistance is writer&amp;#39;s block and
putting jitters and every project that ever shipped late because people
couldn&amp;#39;t stay on the same page long enough to get something out the door.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;- &lt;a href=&quot;http://sethgodin.typepad.com/seths_blog/2010/01/quieting-the-lizard-brain.html&quot; title=&quot;Seth Godin on Quieting the Lizard Brain&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Seth Godin&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My hesitation to write is essentially a hesitation to become vulnerable, which is in
turn a fear of deep emotional connection. I think in some ways, the
always-connected, always-online culture promotes this fear. (There was
an excellent post by someone talking about this that I can&amp;#39;t find anymore. 
So I guess I don&amp;#39;t even know why I mentioned it.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But I&amp;#39;d like to change that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I don&amp;#39;t think it will be easy or natural. I think I will succumb
to The Resistance more often than not. I think it will take practice and
positive reinforcement and courage.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;#39;d like to face this fear. I&amp;#39;d like to be vulnerable. I&amp;#39;d like to be creative.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;#39;d like to write again.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  
 
</feed>
